Yeah, so it's, you know, the fact that the Indian
or the reorganization at Memphis Model
or governments after the US government.
And then in the following years,
it's just been an adoption of very, you know,
wedgenized policies and procedures.
And that falls down into our own governments
of ourselves as people.
And so, you know, we have a travel police force
as slowly been eroding away from a native travel police force
to, you know, predominantly white police thing.
We know our chiefs, a travel member,
you know, all the chiefs have been,
chiefs of police have been travel members.
But a lot of the police people in there are, you know,
predominantly non-Tariky and some of them are, you know,
not even from this, you know, not from the community.
They're from surrounding areas.
But I want to say it's like a goal for us to be in those,
like, impressive places anymore.
My dad was a cop for 17 years.
He was a travel police cop, a police officer
and a state police officer was a bunking county.
And, you know, at one time, I just get a,
the idolization of your father.
You want, I wanted to be a cop, I wanted to do this.
And as, you know, time eroded the sense of that type
of job just kind of was not in the same line
of who we are as native people when that oppression.
You know, we had ways of respecting each other
and keeping an order.
But when you compound that with a, you know,
idea of, you know, a cop being your savior,
you're discreeting those in your community
that are also your savers that your grandma's,
your uncle, your people that truly do listen and understand.
That's what I try to,
try to talk about in a way that, you know,
these pretty critical commits of people
because at this point, a lot of our travel members
go to police forces because it's kind of a last option.
It's a job, it's a good place to go,
to, you know, get benefits and to get a retirement.
But they might not be in the best space,
immediately to be a part of that.
And that's one thing I was learning from a father
was that, like, shouldn't be a cop, you know,
and then hearing that from my mom,
you know, he has, he never talks super negatively,
negatively about his experience,
but it definitely at a point in my adulthood,
he finally told me, but he's glad I was in a cop.
And, and so there's bureaucracy too.
There's, you know, all this other red tape,
but I think they don't think I could feel comfortable
feeling like I'm helpful.
I can only help my people as a cop.
And I hope that our community can reestablish
some type of governments with that,
where they can be, like, those officers
that come to community that reach out to the home,
like my dad said when he was a cop,
they had to go to a house to introduce themselves,
families, they're either at, go to the door,
just get familiar with the community they're in,
so that the community knew that they were talking to.
And that's what's unfortunate right now is that,
not just in, you know, and that sector,
but like there is a disassociation with our community.
And it worries me because if you don't know somebody truly,
and something bad happened out of that, you know,
if they're not experienced,
if they're scared of their word,
one little antidote from my childhood is that some cops
didn't like come up to Big Coat
because it was a considerate rough place.
They would take their time,
which is very troublesome when you need things there
in an immediacy.
And that's my childhood and people might discredit that
saying that was it true.
We are always there, but as in a day when there's a distress
for people that's supposed to take to,
then how's that really serving the community?
But like I said, I don't have a personal experience
with the police here, you know,
it's just other than just like traffic laws, traffic things.
But all I can say from a dad's experience is just,
I think there's a lot that isn't really spoken about.
And I think we need to really take a deeper dive
into community love and to me understanding
so that we can utilize these resources properly
and just utilize them because we have money.
Yeah, and I mean, you look at cops' cities
all over the place, you know,
how can you create, you know, one in Atlanta
with the, you know, what's all happened in the area
specifically with native people.
And you're going to put something that's going to, you know,
in the sense, reignite that type of violence, of suppression.
And I think there's a misconception,
or there's a disconnect on that correlation
that people just think we got to make our cops safer.
We need to make them stronger, you know, we need to do this,
but we're militarizing state and county places.
And the problem with our travel department,
we are the SWAT team in our area.
We're the only, we're only police force with the SWAT team.
So we have to answer calls on non-triple land
and a recent thing you can find where there's some things
where somebody was shot, they sued, we got sued as well
as a tribe because we were the SWAT team.
And to be associated with that, it's like,
why are we putting our next up for a state
that will not allow certain places for sovereignty,
when all allows for certain things to do,
but when it comes to police force and police brutality
and to do this, call them up and then blame them.
And so I say, like, we need to invoke some things
that protect us.
And for me, there's no need, you know,
to have an expensive SWAT vehicle
when our speakers or our language
or our cultural divisions and stuff have to pry grants
and to provide other things
that have to, you know, our teachers are still buying
their own materials.
There is a disconnect and it's just like anywhere else.
I think the mobilization after America is the wrong model.
You know, we had a very nice, it just modeled that
was community-based, community-oriented
and then you're gonna throw in these things
that think protect America when they just,
they elute, they dissolve the idea of what that freedom
and that spirit is.
You know, so that's what worries them.
When all these kids want to turn to be in a cop
or turn to think without having a foundation
of fighting for the community,
I think they're getting the misconception
that this is a good serviceable job
and that we put our next out in a line
and you know, you should have blue eyes matter thing.
But I was like, you know, people don't ask to be shot.
People don't ask to be assaulted.
You know, it's not hard to, you know,
feel for people that being oppressed
and the fact that we go over the amount to Maggie Valley,
every town, every shop has, we back to blue,
all the way down to Maggie Street
where we don't, I don't feel comfortable stopping there.
And it's just simply acknowledging that
why did we have to put so much emphasis on protecting
something that has tanks, assault weapons,
that Kavlar vest, why aren't we focused on protecting people
who are just people and not fact-binding thing else?
I think there's a disconnect.
And again, we have to identify these things
to ensure that people are loved, not weapons and oppression.
But yeah, I think, yeah, I think it's just a disassociation
of ourselves as our ego's, I think we get too ecotistical.
We get to enter ourselves with the gun barricay selfers.
That's not the way to be as we are, you know,
as Ani Dali Giaz as Cherokee is not self-centered.
You shouldn't feel agulation because you're the sole person.
And that's why it's hard because we're a matured.
And so I want to see more women in our, in our places
and being respected, you know, I get a lot leeway,
as much as I, so at things, I don't think a woman
could do as much as I can in our community
without being labeled all back kind of bad things.
I get labeled bad things, but I think it'd be far worse
if somebody was given that space,
because it's just, there's this patriarch
that hides behind that, we're here in San St.
Magicalinio.
And I didn't think we need to acknowledge that
like our women are the power, you know,
the reason I'm so powerful is because I had a four foot
11 grandma who spoke her mind and made sure
that we were respected as an entire community
of Cherokee people.
And she didn't need a colicop to do that.
She didn't need to, you know, do anything.
She just had to, you know, have cousin of cops,
of course she could cut a cousin,
but it wasn't for them, it just helped her out with them.
But, you know, it's just simply, you know,
breaking down that ego, and when we let that ego go,
then these things are just nonsense.
Getting mad about certain things,
I check myself a lot, I have reflections,
my wife's really good about, you know,
having a reflection of my, to acknowledge like,
where there's that overlap that,
that almost regurgitation of some type of,
in hidden patriarchal thing,
but it's good to talk and express,
because like they, we're women, you know,
we don't call it a father town,
we call it a mother town, we can do it.
You know, we don't call Cherokee Nation,
you know, I could have been our brother band,
they're sister tribe, you know, they're that matriarch.
So we didn't respect that.
And when we lose that ego, that male,
mass toxic masculinity, and this like,
allow our women the feminine energy to kind of,
to kind of come back to the forefront.
We're gonna be healthy, we're gonna be successful,
but it's not until we allow that.
And we're just gonna have more infighting,
we're gonna have more arguing, you know,
we're gonna just, you know,
there was no arguing in grandma's house,
because we respected that matriarch.
But there's a lot of arguing now.
So how do we get that same respect,
and allow that respect for everybody that,
you know, truly deserves it.
And I don't think just because you have position of power
means you have power.
I just think you need to utilize it in a better way.
I think these messages need to be heard,
and you know, they're hard, you know,
they're hard to come by sometimes to just sit down
and to wholesome.
I don't like doing video videos,
like I like my heart to speak for itself.
That's why it's very separated from my personal image.
I don't like, same with Luke, you know,
we wanted to create something that wasn't just, you know,
so he did Buffalo Town, so he's known as Buffalo Town.
I'm around the boundary, you know,
it's not our focal point to be the center of attention
to be that, you know, mainstay.
So it's always going to people say,
it's good to see a face with it.
But I think it's not my face,
and it's just speaking, it's the action,
then it's the accumulation of just listening,
and still listening, I still learn so much knowledge,
there's so much knowledge out there from both of you,
you know, both are, and at times,
and my dad carries that, you know,
that that does make your local understanding,
and then my uncle-in-law does that as well,
because they're raised by women,
and those women care those things,
and so it's not to say our men aren't, you know,
or aren't able to do things, and to respect things.
I just think we just have to understand
where that strength comes from,
and it comes from that courtyard,
and I'm really appreciative,
and I hope, you know, my children really respect,
and understand those things too, and value themselves,
you know, have one, you have four kids,
and three of them are girls,
and the last thing I would want them to be,
is feel like they're, oh, somebody's something,
of themselves, I want them to,
you feel like you have all the power,
you have all the strength, you have all the backing.
So these things help me express those things,
because, you know, I love all my kids,
I love all my family, and I just want them to, you know,
feel that they're important,
and everybody's important,
but, and again, using spaces and places like this
to just bring home those points are very helpful,
and something I'm trying to do more of,
because I think we need to occupy these places
that sometimes get discussed with people
that might not be the best fit.